as I expressed earlier. So I think you can come to the table, both being passionate about something. So at least you care. And I would like to believe -- the c-word has also become a horrible word -- "compromise," right? So you have the far left and the far right, and compromise -- forget it. Those groups don't want to even think about it. But you have a huge swath of voters, myself included, who are registered independents, like 40 percent of us, right? So there is a huge faction of America that wants to see change and wants to see people come together. It's just that we have to figure out how to do that. CA: So let's talk about that for a minute, because we're having these TED Dialogues, we're trying to bridge. There's a lot of people out there, right now, perhaps especially on the left, who think this is a terrible idea, that actually, the only moral response to the great tyranny that may be about to emerge in America is to resist it at every stage, is to fight it tooth and nail, it's a mistake to try and do this. Just fight! Is there a case for that? DB: It depends what "fight" means. If it means literal fighting, then no. If it means marching, well maybe marching to raise consciousness, that seems fine. But if you want change in this country, we do it through parties and politics. We organize parties, and those parties are big, diverse, messy coalitions, and we engage in politics, and politics is always morally unsatisfying because it's always a bunch of compromises. But politics is essentially a competition between partial truths. The Trump people have a piece of the truth in America. I think Trump himself is the wrong answer to the right question, but they have some truth, and it's truth found in the epidemic of opiates around the country, it's truth found in the spread of loneliness, it's the truth found in people whose lives are inverted. They peaked professionally at age 30, and it's all been downhill since. And so, understanding that doesn't take fighting, it takes conversation and then asking, "What are we going to replace Trump with?" GC: But you saw fighting last night, even at the speech, because you saw the Democratic women who came and wore white to honor the suffragette movement. I remember back during the campaign where some Trump supporters wanted to actually get rid of the amendment that allowed us to vote as women. It was like, what? So I don't know if that's the right way to fight. It was interesting, because I was looking in the audience, trying to see Democratic women who didn't wear white. So there's a lot going on there, and there's a lot of ways to fight that are not necessarily doing that. CA: I mean, one of the key questions, to me, is: The people who voted for Trump but, if you like, are more in the center, like they're possibly amenable to persuasion -- are they more likely to be persuaded by seeing a passionate uprising of people saying, "No, no, no, you can't!" or will that actually piss them off and push them away? DB: How are any of us persuaded? Am I going to persuade you by saying, "Well, you're kind of a bigot, you're supporting bigotry, you're supporting sexism. You're a primitive, fascistic rise from some authoritarian past"? That's probably not going to be too persuasive to you. And so the way any of us are persuaded is by: a) some basic show of respect for the point of view, and saying, "I think this guy is not going to get you where you need to go." And there are two phrases you've heard over and over again, wherever you go in the country. One, the phrase "flyover country." And that's been heard for years, but I would say this year, I heard it almost on an hourly basis, a sense of feeling invisible. And then the sense a sense of the phrase "political correctness." Just that rebellion: "They're not even letting us say what we think." And I teach at Yale. The narrowing of debate is real. CA: So you would say this is a trap that liberals have fallen into by celebrating causes they really believe in, often expressed through the language of "political correctness." They have done damage. They have pushed people away. DB: I would say a lot of the argument, though, with "descent to fascism," "authoritarianism" -- that just feels over-the-top to people. And listen, I've written eight million anti-Trump columns, but it is a problem, especially for the coastal media, that every time he does something slightly wrong, we go to 11, and we're at 11 every day. And it just strains credibility at some point. CA: Crying wolf a little too loud and a little too early. But there may be a time when we really do have to cry wolf. GC: But see -- one of the most important things to me is how the conservative media handles Trump. Will they call him out when things are not true, or will they just go along with it? To me, that is what is essential in this entire discussion, because when you have followers of somebody who don't really care if he tells the truth or not, that can be very dangerous. So to me, it's: How is the conservative media going to respond to it? I mean, you've been calling them out. But how will other forms of conservative media deal with that as we move forward? DB: It's all shifted, though. The conservative media used to be Fox or Charles Krauthammer or George Will. They're no longer the conservative media. Now there's another whole set of institutions further right, which is Breitbart and Infowars, Alex Jones, Laura Ingraham, and so they're the ones who are now his base, not even so much Fox. CA: My last question for the time being is just on this question of the truth. I mean, it's one of the scariest things to people right now, that there is no agreement, nationally, on what is true. I've never seen anything like it, where facts are so massively disputed. Your whole newspaper, sir, is delivering fake news every day. DB: And failing. (Laughter) CA: And failing. My commiserations. But is there any path whereby we can start to get some kind of consensus, to believe the same things? Can online communities play a role here? How do we fix this? GC: See, I understand how that happened. That's another groundswell kind of emotion that was going on in the middle of America and not being heard, in thinking that the mainstream media was biased. There's a difference, though, between being biased and being fake. To me, that is a very important distinction in this conversation. So let's just say that there was some bias in the mainstream media. OK. So there are ways to try and mend that. But what Trump's doing is nuclearizing that and saying, "Look, we're just going to call all of that fake." That's where it gets dangerous. CA: Do you think enough of his supporters have a greater loyalty to the truth than to any ... Like, the principle of not supporting something that is demonstrably not true actually matters, so there will be a correction at some point? DB: I think the truth eventually comes out. So for example, Donald Trump has based a lot of his economic policy on this supposition that Americans have lost manufacturing jobs because they've been stolen by the Chinese. That is maybe 13 percent of the jobs that left. The truth is that 87 percent of the jobs were replaced by technology. That is just the truth. And so as a result, when he says, "I'm going to close TPP and all the jobs will come roaring back," they will not come roaring back. So that is an actual fact, in my belief. And -- (Laughter) GC: But I'm saying what his supporters think is the truth, no matter how many times you might say that, they still believe him. DB: But eventually either jobs will come back or they will not come back, and at that point, either something will work or it doesn't work, and it doesn't work or not work because of great marketing, it works because it actually addresses a real problem and so I happen to think the truth will out. CA: If you've got a question, please raise your hand here. Yael Eisenstat: I'll speak into the box. My name's Yael Eisenstat. I hear a lot of this talk about how we all need to start talking to each other more and understanding each other more, and I've even written about this, published on this subject as well, but now today I keep hearing liberals -- yes, I live in New York, I can be considered a liberal -- we sit here and self-analyze: What did we do to not understand the Rust Belt? Or: What can we do to understand Middle America better? And what I'd like to know: Have you seen any attempts or conversations from Middle America of what can I do to understand the so-called coastal elites better? Because I'm just offended as being put in a box as a coastal elite as someone in Middle America is as being considered a flyover state and not listened to. CA: There you go, I can hear Facebook cheering as you -- (Laughter) DB: I would say -- and this is someone who has been conservative all my adult life -- when you grow up conservative, you learn to speak both languages. Because if I'm going to listen to music, I'm not going to listen to Ted Nugent. So a lot of my favorite rock bands are all on the left. If I'm going to go to a school, I'm going probably to school where the culture is liberal. If I'm going to watch a sitcom or a late-night comedy show, it's going to be liberal. If I'm going to read a good newspaper, it'll be the New York Times. As a result, you learn to speak both languages. And that actually, at least for a number of years, when I started at National Review with William F. Buckley, it made us sharper, because we were used to arguing against people every day. The problem now that's happened is you have ghettoization on the right and you can live entirely in rightworld, so as a result, the quality of argument on the right has diminished, because you're not in the other side all the time. But I do think if you're living in Minnesota or Iowa or Arizona, the coastal elites make themselves aware to you, so you know that language as well, but it's not the reverse. CA: But what does Middle America not get about coastal elites? So the critique is, you are not dealing with the real problems. There's a feeling of a snobbishness, an elitism that is very off-putting. What are they missing? If you could plant one piece of truth from the mindset of someone in this room, for example, what would you say to them? DB: Just how insanely wonderful we are. (Laughter) No, I reject the category. The problem with populism is the same problem with elitism. It's just a prejudice on the basis of probably an over-generalized social class distinction which is too simplistic to apply in reality. Those of us in New York know there are some people in New York who are completely awesome, and some people who are pathetic, and if you live in Iowa, some people are awesome and some people are pathetic. It's not a question of what degree you have or where you happen to live in the country. The distinction is just a crude simplification to arouse political power. GC: But I would encourage people to watch a television news show or read a column that they normally wouldn't. So if you are a Trump supporter, watch the other side for a day, because you need to come out of the bubble if you're ever going to have a conversation. And both sides -- so if you're a liberal, then watch something that's very conservative. Read a column that is not something you would normally read, because then you gain perspective of what the other side is thinking, and to me, that's a start of coming together. I worry about the same thing you worry about, these bubbles. I think if you only watch certain entities, you have no idea what the rest of the world is talking about. DB: I think not only watching, being part of an organization that meets at least once a month that puts you in direct contact with people completely unlike yourself is something we all have a responsibility for. I may get this a little wrong, but I think of the top-selling automotive models in this country, I think the top three or four are all pickup trucks. So ask yourself: How many people do I know who own a pickup truck? And it could be very few or zero for a lot of people. And that's sort of a warning sign kind of a problem. Where can I join a club where I'll have a lot in common with a person who drives a pickup truck because we have a common interest in whatever? CA: And so the internet is definitely contributing to this. A question here from Chris Ajemian: "How do you feel structure of communications, especially the prevalence of social media and individualized content, can be used to bring together a political divide, instead of just filing communities into echo chambers?" I mean, it looks like Facebook and Google, since the election, are working hard on this question. They're trying to change the algorithms so that they don't amplify fake news to the extent that it happened last time round. Do you see any other promising signs of ...? GC: ... or amplify one side of the equation. CA: Exactly. GC: I think that was the constant argument from the right, that social media and the internet in general was putting articles towards the top that were not their worldview. I think, again, that fed into the anger. It fed into the anger of: "You're pushing something that's not what I believe." But social media has obviously changed everything, and I think Trump is the example of Twitter changing absolutely everything. And from his point of view, he's reaching the American people without a filter, which he believes the media is. CA: Question from the audience. Destiny: Hi. I'm Destiny. I have a question regarding political correctness, and I'm curious: When did political correctness become synonymous with silencing, versus a way that we speak about other people to show them respect and preserve their dignity? GC: Well, I think the conservative media really pounded this issue for the last 10 years. I think that they really, really spent a lot of time talking about political correctness, and how people should have the ability to say what they think. Another reason why Trump became so popular: because he says what he thinks. It also makes me think about the fact that I do believe there are a lot of people in America who agree with Steve Bannon, but they would never say it publicly, and so voting for Trump gave them the opportunity to agree with it silently. DB: On the issue of immigration, it's a legitimate point of view that we have too many immigrants in the country, that it's economically costly. CA: That we have too many -- DB: Immigrants in the country, especially from Britain. (Laughter) GC: I kind of like the British accent, OK? CA: I apologize. America, I am sorry. (Laughter) I'll go now. DB: But it became sort of impermissible to say that, because it was a sign that somehow you must be a bigot of some sort. So the political correctness was not only cracking down on speech that we would all find completely offensive, it was cracking down on some speech that was legitimate, and then it was turning speech and thought into action and treating it as a crime, and people getting fired and people thrown out of schools, and there were speech codes written. Now there are these diversity teams, where if you say something that somebody finds offensive, like, "Smoking is really dangerous," you can say "You're insulting my group," and the team from the administration will come down into your dorm room and put thought police upon you. And so there has been a genuine narrowing of what is permissible to say. And some of it is legitimate. There are certain words that there should be some social sanction against, but some of it was used to enforce a political agenda. CA: So is that a project you would urge on liberals, if you like -- progressives -- to rethink the ground rules around political correctness and accept a little more uncomfortable language in certain circumstances? Can you see that being solved to an extent that others won't be so offended? DB: I mean, most American universities, especially elite universities, are overwhelmingly on the left, and there's just an ease of temptation to use your overwhelming cultural power to try to enforce some sort of thought that you think is right and correct thought. So, be a little more self-suspicious of, are we doing that? And second, my university, the University of Chicago, sent out this letter saying, we will have no safe spaces. There will be no critique of micro-aggression. If you get your feelings hurt, well, welcome to the world of education. I do think that policy -- which is being embraced by a lot of people on the left, by the way -- is just a corrective to what's happened. CA: So here's a question from Karen Holloway: How do we foster an American culture that's forward-looking, like Hamilton, that expects and deals with change, rather than wanting to have everything go back to some fictional past? That's an easy question, right? GC: Well, I'm still a believer in the American dream, and I think what we can teach our children is the basics, which is that hard work and believing in yourself in America, you can achieve whatever you want. I was told that every single day. When I got in the real world, I was like, wow, that's maybe not always so true. But I still believe in that. Maybe I'm being too optimistic. So I still look towards the future for that to continue. DB: I think you're being too optimistic. GC: You do? DB: The odds of an American young person exceeding their parents' salary -- a generation ago, like 86 percent did it. Now 51 percent do it. There's just been a problem in social mobility in the country. CA: You've written that this entire century has basically been a disaster, that the age of sunny growth is over and we're in deep trouble. DB: Yeah, I mean, we averaged, in real terms, population-adjusted, two or three percent growth for 50 years, and now we've had less than one percent growth. And so there's something seeping out. And so if I'm going to tell people that they should take risks, one of the things we're seeing is a rapid decline in mobility, the number of people who are moving across state lines, and that's especially true among millennials. It's young people that are moving less. So how do we give people the security from which they can take risk? And I'm a big believer in attachment theory of raising children, and attachment theory is based on the motto that all of life is a series of daring adventures from a secure base. Have you parents given you a secure base? And as a society, we do not have a secure base, and we won't get to that "Hamilton," risk-taking, energetic ethos until we can supply a secure base. CA: So I wonder whether there's ground here to create almost like a shared agenda, a bridging conversation, on the one hand recognizing that there is this really deep problem that the system, the economic system that we built, seems to be misfiring right now. Second, that maybe, if you're right that it's not all about immigrants, it's probably more about technology, if you could win that argument, that de-emphasizes what seems to me the single most divisive territory between Trump supporters and others, which is around the role of the other. It's very offensive to people on the left to have the other demonized to the extent that the other seems to be demonized. That feels deeply immoral, and maybe people on the left could agree, as you said, that immigration may have happened too fast, and there is a limit beyond which human societies struggle, but nonetheless this whole problem becomes de-emphasized if automation is the key issue, and then we try to work together on recognizing that it's real, recognizing that the problem probably wasn't properly addressed or seen or heard, and try to figure out how to rebuild communities using, well, using what? That seems to me to become the fertile conversation of the future: How do we rebuild communities in this modern age, with technology doing what it's doing, and reimagine this bright future? GC: That's why I go back to optimism. I'm not being ... it's not like I'm not looking at the facts, where we've come or where we've come from. But for gosh sakes, if we don't look at it from an optimistic point of view -- I'm refusing to do that just yet. I'm not raising my 12- and 13-year-old to say, "Look, the world is dim." CA; We're going to have one more question from the room here. Questioner: Hi. Hello. Sorry. You both mentioned the infrastructure plan and Russia and some other things that wouldn't be traditional Republican priorities. What do you think, or when, will Republicans be motivated to take a stand against Trumpism? GC: After last night, not for a while. He changed a lot last night, I believe. DB: His popularity among Republicans -- he's got 85 percent approval, which is higher than Reagan had at this time, and that's because society has just gotten more polarized. So people follow the party much more than they used to. So if you're waiting for Paul Ryan and the Republicans in Congress to flake away, it's going to take a little while. GC: But also because they're all concerned about reelection, and Trump has so much power with getting people either for you or against you, and so, they're vacillating every day, probably: "Well, should I go against or should I not?" But last night, where he finally sounded presidential, I think most Republicans are breathing a sigh of relief today. DB: The half-life of that is short. GC: Right -- I was just going to say, until Twitter happens again. CA: OK, I want to give each of you the chance to imagine you're speaking to -- I don't know -- the people online who are watching this, who may be Trump supporters,
como expresé antes. Creo que se puede negociar siendo apasionado acerca de algo. Porque al menos te importa. Me gustaría creer que la palabra con c se ha vuelto una palabra horrible, "compromiso", ¿cierto? Tenemos la izquierda y la derecha extrema, y el compromiso... olvídenlo. Esos grupos ni siquiera quieren pensar en ello, Pero hay una masa de votantes, incluyéndome a mí, registrados como independientes, como el 40 % de nosotros. Hay una gran fracción de EE. UU. que quiere ver un cambio y que quiere que la gente se una. Solo tenemos que encontrar la manera de hacerlo. CA: Hablemos de eso por un minuto, porque estamos teniendo estos diálogos TED para acortar brechas. Hay mucha gente allá afuera, quizá de izquierda, que piensan que esto es una mala idea que la única respuesta moral a la tiranía que quizá esté a punto de surgir en EE. UU. sea resistir cada etapa, luchar con uñas y dientes, es un error intentar hacer esto. ¡A pelear! ¿Hay algún motivo para eso? DB: Depende de lo que "pelear" signifique. Si es pelear literalmente, no. Si significa marchar, quizás, marchar para despertar consciencia, está bien. Pero si quieren cambiar este país, debe ser mediante partidos y política. Organizamos partidos y estos son grandes coaliciones diversas y desordenados, y participamos en política, la política es siempre moralmente insatisfactoria porque siempre se trata de un montón de compromisos. La política es una competencia entre verdades parciales. La gente de Trump tiene parte de la verdad en EE. UU. Creo que Trump es la respuesta incorrecta a la pregunta correcta, pero tienen algo de la verdad, verdad encontrada en la epidemia de los opiáceos del país, verdad encontrada en la propagación de la soledad, verdad encontrada en la gente con vidas invertidas. Alcanzaron el apogeo a los 30 años de edad y van cuesta abajo desde entonces. Así, entendiendo que no se necesita pelear sino conversar y preguntar, "¿con qué vamos a reemplazar a Trump?". GC: Pero vieron peleas anoche, incluso en el discurso, vieron a las mujeres demócratas que fueron vestidas de blanco para honorar el movimiento sufragista. Recuerdo que durante la campaña algunos simpatizantes de Trump querían deshacerse de la enmienda que permitía a las mujeres votar. No podíamos creerlo. No sé si esa sea la manera adecuada de pelear. Fue interesante mirar a la audiencia y ver a mujeres demócratas que no vestían de blanco. Hubo muchas cosas ahí, y muchas maneras de pelear sin necesidad de pelear. CA: Una de las preguntas claves para mí es: La gente que votó por Trump que pertenece un poco al centro, como si fuesen susceptibles a la persuasión, ¿son más propensos a ser persuadidos al ver un levantamiento apasionado de gente diciendo, "¡No, no, no pueden!", o eso los enfadaría y alejaría? DB: ¿Cómo somos persuadidos? ¿Voy a persuadirte diciéndote "Eres un fanático, estás apoyando la intolerancia, estás apoyando el sexismo. ¿Eres el surgimiento fascista de algún pasado autoritario?". Quizá eso no les parezca muy persuasivo. Las maneras en que se persuade son: a) una muestra de respecto básica respecto a tu perspectiva, decir, "Creo que este tipo no te llevará a donde tú necesitas llegar". Hay dos frases que han escuchado una y otra vez, a donde vayan en el país. Una, la frase "país de sobrevuelo". Se ha escuchado durante años, yo diría que este año, lo escuché casi cada hora, un sentido de ser invisible. Luego, el sentido de la frase "la corrección política". Solo esa rebelión: "Ni siquiera nos dejan decir lo que pensamos". Y yo enseño en Yale. El estrechamiento del debate es real. CA: Dirían que es una trampa en que los liberales han caído al celebrar las causas en las que ellos creen, a menudo expresado a través del lenguaje de la "corrección política". Han hecho daño. Han alejado a la gente. DB: Yo diría que el argumento es, "descender al fascismo" "autoritarianismo", que la gente siente exagerado. He escrito ocho millones de columnas anti-Trump, pero es un problema, en especial para los medios costeros que cada vez que él comete un error incluso menor, hacemos alboroto, y nos alborotamos cada día. Eso dificulta la credibilidad hasta cierto punto. CA: Dar falsa alarma muy alto y demasiado pronto. Quizá haya un momento en que debamos dar alarma. GC: Verán, una de las cosas más importantes para mí, es cómo los medios conservadores manejan a Trump. Cuando las cosas no sean ciertas, ¿las señalarán o solo las aceptarán? Para mí, eso es esencial en esta discusión, porque cuando se tiene simpatizantes a quienes no les importa si él dice la verdad o no, podría ser muy peligroso. Me pregunto, ¿Cómo van a responder los medios conservadores? Tú los has desafiado. ¿Cómo van a tratarlo otros medios conservadores en lo subsiguiente? DB: Todo ha cambiado. Los medios conservadores eran Fox, Charles Krauthammer o George Will. Ya no son conservadores. Ahora hay otro set de instituciones de extrema derecha, Breitbart e Inforwars, Alex Jones, Laura Ingraham, ahora ellos son la base, Fox ya no tanto. CA: Mi última pregunta en este momento es respecto a la cuestión de la verdad. Es una de las cosas más aterradoras para la gente ahorita, no hay un acuerdo nacional sobre lo que es verdad. Nunca había visto algo así, donde los hechos son disputados de manera masiva. Su periódico, señor, proporciona noticias falsas todos los días. DB: Y con errores. (Risas) CA: Y con errores. Mis conmiseraciones. ¿Hay algún camino por el cual podamos comenzar a llegar a acuerdos, para creer en las mismas cosas? ¿Podrán las comunidades en línea jugar algún papel en esto? ¿Cómo lo arreglamos? GC: Comprendo cómo ocurrió. Fue otra oleada de emoción que ocurrió en el centro de EE. UU. sin ser escuchada, creo que los medios dominantes fueron tendenciosos. Aunque es distinto ser tendencioso a ser falso. Esa distinción es muy importante en esta conversación. Digamos que los medios dominantes fueron un poco tendenciosos. Hay maneras de remendar eso. Pero Trump lo está acaparando y dice, "Miren, vamos a llamarle falso a todo". Ahí se vuelve peligroso. CA: ¿Creen que suficientes simpatizantes sean más leales a la verdad que a cualquier... Por ejemplo, el principio de no apoyar algo que se ha demostrado que es falso realmente importa, habrá rectificación en algún punto? DB: La verdad eventualmente sale a la luz. Por ejemplo, Trump ha basado gran parte de su política económica en que se han perdido muchos empleos manufactureros porque los chinos los han robado. Es quizá el 13 % de los empleos que desaparecieron. La verdad es que la tecnología reemplazó el 87 % de los empleos. Esa es la verdad. Como resultado, cuando él dice, "Voy a cerrar el TPP y los empleos regresarán bulliciosamente", no van a regresar. Eso es un hecho, es mi creencia. Y... (Risas) GC: Pero digo que lo que sus simpatizantes creen que es verdad, sin importar cuántas veces lo digas, ellos aún le creen. DB: Pero finalmente los trabajos regresarán o no regresarán, y en ese momento, o funcionará o no funcionará, y si no funciona o deja de funcionar por un gran mercadeo, funciona porque en verdad aborda un problema real así que se me ocurre que la verdad saldrá a la luz. CA: Si tienen alguna pregunta por favor levanten la mano. Yael Eisenstat: Hablaré hacia la caja. Mi nombre es Yael Eisenstat. He escuchado mucho esta charla sobre cómo necesitamos hablarnos más entre nosotros y entendernos más, e incluso he escrito y publicado respecto al tema también, pero hoy en día sigo escuchando liberales --sí, vivo en Nueva York, me considero liberal-- nos sentamos aquí para autoanalizamos: ¿Qué hicimos para no entender el Rust Belt? O: ¿qué podemos hacer para entender mejor el centro de EE. UU.? Y me gustaría saber: ¿Han visto algún intento o conversación del centro de EE. UU. de cómo entender mejor a las élites costeras? Porque me ofende que me clasifiquen solo como élite costera como a alguien del centro le ofende que lo consideren estado de sobrevuelo y que no se nos escuche. CA: Muy bien, puedo escuchar el Facebook aclamándote... (Risas) DB: Yo diría --y habla alguien que ha sido conservador toda su vida adulta-- cuando creces siendo conservador, aprendes a hablar ambos idiomas. Porque si voy a escuchar música, voy a escuchar a Ted Nugent. Muchas de mis bandas preferidas son de izquierda. Si voy a ir a una escuela, probablemente iré a una escuela donde la cultura es liberal. Si voy a mirar una comedia o un show de comedia nocturno, va a ser liberal. Si voy a leer un buen periódico, será el New York Times. Como resultado, aprendes ambos idiomas. Y así, al menos por una cantidad de años, cuando comencé en National Review con William F. Buckley, nos hizo más mordaces, porque estábamos acostumbrados a discutir con gente día a día. El problema ahora es que hay como un ghetto en la derecha, puedes vivir todo en el mundo de derecha, por eso, la calidad de los argumentos de derecha ha disminuido, porque no te pones en el otro lado todo el tiempo. Creo que si vives en Minnesota, Iowa o Arizona, las élites costeras se vuelven visibles para ti, así que conoces ese idioma también, pero no a la inversa. CA: ¿Qué es lo que el centro de EE. UU. no comprende de las élites costeras? La crítica es, no estás tratando con los problemas reales. Hay un sentimiento de pedantería, un elitismo desmoralizador. ¿Qué se están perdiendo? Si pudieran plantar una pieza de verdad desde la mentalidad de alguien en esta sala, por ejemplo, ¿qué les dirían? DB: Cuán fantásticos somos. (Risas) No, rechazo la categoría. El problema con el populismo es el mismo que el del elitismo. Solo hay prejuicio en su base, o quizá una sobregeneralizada distinción de clases la cual es muy simplista para aplicarse en la realidad. Los que estamos en Nueva York sabemos que hay gente ahí que es muy agradable, y otra que es patética, y si vives en Iowa, algunos son agradables y otros son patéticos. No es una cuestión de qué grado tienes o en dónde vives en el país. La distinción es una simplificación cruda para suscitar poder político. GC: Me gustaría animar a la gente a ver las noticias o a leer una columna que no leerían normalmente. Y si eres simpatizante de Trump, mira al otro lado un día, porque necesitas salir de la burbuja si quieres tener una conversación. Para ambos lados; si eres liberal, mira algo que sea conservador. Lee una columna que normalmente no leerías, porque así adquieres perspectiva de lo que el otro lado piensa, y ese es el primer paso para estar unidos. Me preocupan lo mismo que a ti, esas burbujas. Si solo miras algunas instituciones, no tendrás idea de lo que está hablando el resto del mundo. DB: No solo se trata de mirar, sino ser parte de una organización que se reúna una vez al mes que te ponga en contacto directo con gente totalmente distinta a ti es responsabilidad de todos. Quizá esté un poco errado, pero los modelos de autos que más se venden en el país, los tres o cuatro primeros son camionetas. Pregúntense: ¿cuántas personas que conozco tienen una camioneta? Podrían ser muy pocas incluso cero para mucha gente. Ese es un signo de alerta. ¿Dónde hay un club para unirme que tenga mucho en común con una persona que maneje una camioneta porque tenemos un interés común en algo? CA: El internet contribuye en esto. Una pregunta de Chris Ajemian: "¿Qué opinan de que las comunicaciones, en especial las redes sociales y el contenido individualizado, puedan ser usados para unir una división política, en vez de guardar comunidades en cámaras de eco?". Parece que Facebook y Google, desde la elección, han trabajado duro en esta cuestión. Han intentado cambiar los algoritmos para no difundir noticias falsas porque pasó la última vez. ¿Ven alguna otra señal prometedora...? GC: ... o difundir un lado de la ecuación. CA: Exactamente. GC: Creo que ese ha sido el argumento constante de la derecha, que las redes sociales y el internet en general pusieron artículos a la cabeza que no eran su visión del mundo. Considero que eso alimentó el enojo. Alimentó el enojo de: "Están promoviendo algo en lo que yo no creo". Las redes sociales lo han cambiado todo obviamente, y Trump es el ejemplo de que Twitter ha cambiado absolutamente todo. Desde su perspectiva, él se ha acercado a los estadounidenses sin ningún filtro, el que para él son los medios. CA: Pregunta de la audiencia. Destiny: Hola. Soy Destiny. Tengo una pregunta respecto a la corrección política: ¿Cuándo la corrección política se convirtió en sinónimo del silencio, frente a la manera de hablar de otras personas para mostrarles respeto y preservar su dignidad? GC: Creo que los medios conservadores afectaron esta situación en los últimos 10 años. Emplearon realmente mucho tiempo hablando de la corrección política, y cómo la gente debía tener la habilidad para decir lo que pensaba. Otra razón para que Trump se volviera tan popular: él dice lo que piensa. También me hace pensar en el hecho de que mucha gente en EE. UU. está de acuerdo con Steve Bannon, pero no lo admitirían públicamente, y votar por Trump les dio la oportunidad de estar de acuerdo silenciosamente. DB: Sobre la cuestión de inmigración es un punto de vista legítimo que tenemos demasiados inmigrantes en el país, eso es económicamente costoso. CA: Que tenemos demasiados... DB: Inmigrantes en el país, en especial de Gran Bretaña. (Risas) GC: Como que me gusta el acento británico. CA: Me disculpo. EE. UU., lo lamento. (Risas) Me iré de inmediato. DB: Ya no es permitido decirlo, porque se volvió una señal de que eras un fanático de algún tipo. La corrección política no solo se estaba poniendo dura con los discursos que todos encontramos completamente ofensivos, sino también con discursos legítimos, y pasó del discurso y el pensamiento a la acción y lo tachó de crimen, mucha gente fue despedida, o expulsada de las escuelas, y se escribieron reglas de discurso. Ahora hay grupos diversos, donde si dices algo que alguien encuentre ofensivo, como, "fumar es peligroso", pueden decirte "nos estás insultando", y el equipo administrativo vendrá a la puerta de tu dormitorio y te pondrá a un policía del pensamiento. Se ha reducido considerablemente lo que es permisible decir. Algo de eso a veces es legítimo. Hay ciertas palabras que deberían ser sancionadas de manera social, algo de eso se usó para imponer una agenda política. CA: ¿Es ese un proyecto que se instauraría en los liberales, --o progresistas-- para reconsiderar las reglas básicas de la corrección política y aceptar un lenguaje un poco menos incómodo en determinadas circunstancias? ¿Creen que eso se resuelva al punto de que otros no se sientan ofendidos? DB: Muchas universidades de EE. UU., en especial las de élite, son en demasía de izquierda, y hay una tentación de usar su gran poder cultural que pensarían es justo y correcto. ¿Hay que desconfiar de uno mismo o, eso está pasando? Por otra parte, mi universidad, la Universidad de Chicago, envió una carta diciendo que no tenemos lugares seguros. No habrá crítica de microagresión. Si hieren tus sentimientos, bueno, bienvenido al mundo de la educación. Creo que esa política --la cual es ser acogido por mucha gente de izquierda, por cierto-- es un correctivo de lo que ha ocurrido. CA: Karen Holloway tiene una pregunta: ¿Cómo adoptar una cultura estadounidense que tiene miras al futuro, como Hamilton, que ansía y maneja el cambio, en lugar de querer regresar a un pasado ficticio queriendo tenerlo todo? Es una pregunta fácil, ¿no? GC: Bueno, soy un creyente del sueño americano, y podemos enseñarle a nuestros hijos lo básico, o sea, que con el trabajo duro y con creer en ti mismo en EE. UU., puedes alcanzar lo que quieras. Me lo decían todos los días. Cuando llegué al mundo real, pensé, oh, quizá no sea del todo verdad. Pero aún creo en eso. Quizá sea muy optimista. Y espero que en el futuro aún sea así. DB: Creo que eres demasiado optimista. GC: ¿Lo crees? DB: La probabilidad de que un joven supere el salario de sus padres... un 86 % de la generación pasada lo logró. Ahora el 51 % lo logra. Hay un problema de movilidad social aquí. CA: Has escrito que todo este siglo ha sido un desastre, básicamente, que la edad de crecimiento se acabó y que estamos en verdaderos problemas. DB: Sí en promedio a escala de población hemos crecido un 2 o 3 % en 50 años, y ahora menos del 1 %. Algo se nos está escapando. Si le voy a decir a la gente que tome riesgos, estamos viendo un declive acelerado en la movilidad en el número de gente cruzando las fronteras estatales, es cierto en especial entre millennials. Es gente joven que me mueve menos. ¿Cómo le damos a la gente la seguridad de que pueden tomar riesgos? Creo en la teoría del apego para criar hijos, y ésta tiene por lema que la vida es una serie de aventuras riesgosas vividas desde una base estable. ¿Tus padres te han dado una base estable? Como sociedad no tenemos una, y no podremos llegar a ese ethos enérgico y riesgoso estilo Hamilton hasta que proveamos una base estable. CA: Me pregunto si hay razones para crear una agenda compartida, un diálogo para acortar brechas, por una parte, reconociendo que hay un problema muy serio que el sistema económico que creamos, parece fallar en estos momentos. Por otra parte, si están en lo correcto de que no son los inmigrantes, sino más bien la tecnología, si pudieran ganar ese argumento, que atenúa lo que me parece es el único y más divisivo territorio entre los simpatizantes de Trump y los demás, que es el rol de los demás. Es ofensivo para la izquierda satanizar a los demás al punto en que aquéllos sean realmente vistos como tal. Esto se siente en demasía inmoral, y quizá la gente de izquierda concuerde, como mencionaste, en que la inmigración ha pasado muy rápido, y que hay un límite más allá de lo que la sociedad puede manejar, sin embargo, este problema se atenúa si la automatización es el punto clave, y trabajamos juntos reconociendo que es real, reconociendo que el problema no fue apropiadamente abordado visto o escuchado, y encontramos cómo reconstruir comunidades usando, ¿usando qué? Esa parece ser la conversación fértil del futuro: ¿Cómo reconstruir comunidades en la edad moderna, con la tecnología haciendo lo que hace, y reimaginar un futuro brillante? GC: Por eso recurro al optimismo, no soy... no es que no mire los hechos, a dónde hemos llegado o de dónde venimos. Pero, por Dios, si no miramos desde una perspectiva optimista... me rehúso a no hacerlo. No estoy educando a mis hijos de 12 y 13 para que digan "el mundo es sombrío". CA: Tomaremos otra pregunta de la audiencia. Interrogador: Hola, hola. Disculpen. Ambos mencionaron que el plan de infraestructura y Rusia y otras cosas no son prioridades tradicionalmente republicanas. ¿Cuándo creen que los republicanos se animarán a pronunciarse en contra del trumpismo? GC: Después de lo de anoche, no en mucho tiempo. Mucho cambió anoche, creo yo. DB: Su popularidad entre los republicanos, tiene el 85 % de la aprobación, que es más alto de lo que tuvo Reagan, y es así porque la sociedad se polarizó más. La gente sigue al partido mucho más de lo que solían. Si esperan que Paul Ryan y los republicanos en el Congreso se desprendan, va a tomar un tiempo. GC: Pero también porque a todos les preocupa la reelección, y Trump tiene tanto poder poniendo gente a favor o en contra, que vacilan cada día, quizás: "¿Debo o no debo estar a favor?". Anoche, cuando al fin sonó como presidente, los republicanos deben estar respirando aliviados hoy. DB: Esa media vida es corta. CG: Cierto. Eso iba a decir, hasta Twitter pasó otra vez. CA: Bien, quiero darles una oportunidad para que imaginen que están hablando con --no sé-- la gente en línea que está viendo esto, que quizá apoyen a Trump,
who may be on the left, somewhere in the middle. How would you advise them to bridge or to relate to other people? Can you share any final wisdom on this? Or if you think that they shouldn't, tell them that as well. GC: I would just start by saying that I really think any change and coming together starts from the top, just like any other organization. And I would love if, somehow, Trump supporters or people on the left could encourage their leaders to show that compassion from the top, because imagine the change that we could have if Donald Trump tweeted out today, to all of his supporters, "Let's not be vile anymore to each other. Let's have more understanding. As a leader, I'm going to be more inclusive to all of the people of America." To me, it starts at the top. Is he going to do that? I have no idea. But I think that everything starts from the top, and the power that he has in encouraging his supporters to have an understanding of where people are coming from on the other side. CA: David. DB: Yeah, I guess I would say I don't think we can teach each other to be civil, and give us sermons on civility. That's not going to do it. It's substance and how we act, and the nice thing about Donald Trump is he smashed our categories. All the categories that we thought we were thinking in, they're obsolete. They were great for the 20th century. They're not good for today. He's got an agenda which is about closing borders and closing trade. I just don't think it's going to work. I think if we want to rebuild communities, recreate jobs, we need a different set of agenda that smashes through all our current divisions and our current categories. For me, that agenda is Reaganism on macroeconomic policy, Sweden on welfare policy and cuts across right and left. I think we have to have a dynamic economy that creates growth. That's the Reagan on economic policy. But people have to have that secure base. There have to be nurse-family partnerships; there has to be universal preschool; there have to be charter schools; there have to be college programs with wraparound programs for parents and communities. We need to help heal the crisis of social solidarity in this country and help heal families, and government just has to get a lot more involved in the way liberals like to rebuild communities. At the other hand, we have to have an economy that's free and open the way conservatives used to like. And so getting the substance right is how you smash through the partisan identities, because the substance is what ultimately shapes our polarization. CA: David and Gretchen, thank you so much for an absolutely fascinating conversation. Thank you. That was really, really interesting. (Applause) Hey, let's keep the conversation going. We're continuing to try and figure out whether we can add something here, so keep the conversation going on Facebook. Give us your thoughts from whatever part of the political spectrum you're on, and actually, wherever in the world you are. This is not just about America. It's about the world, too. But we're not going to end today without music, because if we put music in every political conversation, the world would be completely different, frankly. It just would. (Applause) Up in Harlem, this extraordinary woman, Vy Higginsen, who's actually right here -- let's get a shot of her. (Applause) She created this program that brings teens together, teaches them the joy and the impact of gospel music, and hundreds of teens have gone through this program. It's transformative for them. The music they made, as you already heard, is extraordinary, and I can't think of a better way of ending this TED Dialogue than welcoming Vy Higginsen's Gospel Choir from Harlem. Thank you. (Applause) (Singing) Choir: O beautiful for spacious skies For amber waves of grain For purple mountain majesties Above the fruited plain America! God shed his grace on thee And crown thy good with brotherhood From sea to shining sea (Applause)
o que sean de izquierda, o de centro. ¿Cómo les aconsejarían acortar brechas y relacionarse con los demás? ¿Podrían compartir su sabiduría en esto? O si creen que no deban, díganselo. GC: Quiero comenzar diciendo que cualquier cambio y unión viene de arriba, como en cualquier organización. Me encantaría que un día, los simpatizantes de Trump, o la gente de derecha, animaran a sus líderes a mostrar compasión desde arriba, porque imaginen el cambio que podríamos tener si hoy Trump twitteara, para todos sus simpatizantes, "No seamos malvados con nadie más. Entendámonos más. Como líder, seré más inclusivo con toda la gente de EE. UU.". Para mí, comienza desde arriba. ¿Va a hacer algo así? No tengo idea. Pero creo que todo comienza desde arriba, y el poder que él tiene para alentar a sus simpatizantes a comprender de dónde viene la gente del otro lado. CA: David. DB: Sí, yo diría que no creo que podamos enseñarles a otros a ser civiles, y dar sermones de civilidad. No funcionará. Es la substancia y nuestro actuar, lo bueno de Trump es que rompió nuestras categorías. Todas las categorías que creíamos tener, están obsoletas. Fueron buenas para siglo XX. No lo son para hoy. Su agenda se trata de cerrar las fronteras y el comercio. No creo que vaya a funcionar. Si queremos reconstruir comunidades, crear empleos, necesitamos otro tipo de agenda que termine con nuestras actuales divisiones y categorías. Esa agenda es el reaganismo o política macroeconómica, En Suecia su política de bienestar trasciende a la izquierda y a la derecha. Debemos tener una economía dinámica para estimular el crecimiento. Es la política económica de Reagan. Pero la gente necesita una base estable. Necesitamos asociaciones de enfermeros y familias; preescolar universal; debe haber escuelas subvencionadas: debe haber programas universitarios envolventes para padres y comunidades. Necesitamos ayuda para sanar la crisis de solidaridad social y ayudar a curar familias, el gobierno tiene que involucrarse más en la manera en que a los liberales les gusta reconstruir comunidades. Necesitamos tener la economía libre y abierta que solía gustarles a los conservadores. Si la substancia es la correcta podemos atravesar las identidades partidistas, porque la substancia forma nuestra polarización. CA: David y Gretchen, muchas gracias por una absolutamente fascinante charla. Gracias. Fue muy interesante. (Aplausos) Hay que continuar esta conversación. Tratamos de encontrar si se puede agregar algo más, continuemos la charla por Facebook. Díganos qué piensan desde su postura política, cualquiera que sea, y desde donde se encuentren en el mundo. Esto no solo se trata de EE. UU., sino de todo el mundo. Terminaremos hoy sin música, porque si ponemos música en cada charla de política, el mundo sería un lugar distinto, créanme. Lo sería simplemente. (Aplausos) Esta extraordinaria mujer del Harlem, Vy Higginsen, quien se encuentra aquí... veamos una toma de ella. (Aplausos) Ella creó un programa que une a los adolescentes, les enseña la alegría e impacto de la música góspel, y cientos de adolescentes han estado en ese programa. Es transformador para ellos. La música que componen, como habrán escuchado, es extraordinaria, no se me ocurre una mejor manera de concluir este diálogo TED démosle la bienvenida al Coro de Góspel del Harlem de Vy Higginsen. Gracias. (Aplausos) (Cantando) Coro: Oh hermosos y amplios cielos Por olas de grano ámbar Por majestuosas montañas púrpura Arriba de un llano frutal ¡América! Dios derramó su gracia sobre ti Y coronó a tu Dios con la hermandad Desde el mar al mar radiante (Aplausos)